哈尔滨工业大学 IBM技术中心
倾情制作
校对：吴　晋（Cliff Woo）
字幕：邓雄飞（Dysprosium）
时间轴：邓雄飞（Dysprosium)
特别感谢：裘宗燕
欢迎大家来一起学习这门计算机科学的基础课程
I'd like to welcome you to this course on computer science.
事实上 以这样的方式来表述并不恰当
Actually, that's a terrible way to start.
于此来说 计算机科学是个糟糕的名字
Computer science is a terrible name for this business.
首先 它不算是一门科学
First of all, it's not a science.
它更应该被称为工程或者是艺术
It might be engineering or it might be art,
但我们实际上会发现 这个所谓的计算机科学
but we'll actually see that computer so-called science
却与魔法一样的有众多神奇之处
actually has a lot in common with magic,
这些将会在课程中一一体现
and we'll see that in this course.
所以 不能称其为一门科学
So it's not a science.
这门学科和“计算机”也并非紧密相关
It's also not really very much about computers.
类似的 就像我们说
And it's not about computers in the same sense
物理学中并不仅仅有关粒子加速器
that physics is not really about particle accelerators,
生物学中并不全然是显微镜和培养皿一样
and biology is not really about microscopes and petri dishes.
同理
And it's not about computers in the same sense
几何学中也并不全是介绍如何使用测量仪器
that geometry is not really about using surveying instruments.
事实上 计算机科学和几何学有很多共性
In fact, there's a lot of commonality between computer science and geometry.
首先 几何学
Geometry, first of all,
只是另一个有个糟糕名字的学科
is another subject with a lousy name.
这个名字来自于Gaia 意为土地
The name comes from Gaia, meaning the Earth,
以及metron 意为测量
and metron, meaning to measure.
几何学最初意为测地或者勘探
Geometry originally meant measuring the Earth or surveying.
这是因为数千年前的埃及祭司
And the reason for that was that, thousands of years ago,
为了计算如何去修复年年被尼罗河的洪水
the Egyptian priesthood developed the rudiments of geometry
所毁坏的牧田边界
in order to figure out how to restore the boundaries of fields
而建立了几何学基础
that were destroyed in the annual flooding of the Nile.
而对出于这个目的的埃及人来说
And to the Egyptians who did that,
几何学的确是掌握对测量仪器的使用
geometry really was the use of surveying instruments.
现在 我们以为计算机科学就是介绍计算机的使用
Now, the reason that we think computer science is about computers
就正如埃及人认为
is pretty much the same reason that the Egyptians thought geometry
几何学是介绍如何使用测量仪器的
was about surveying instruments.
换句话说 任何一门学科起步的时候
And that is, when some field is just getting started
你都对它了解不深
and you don't really understand it very well,
这很容易使你混淆所做的事与所用之物
it's very easy to confuse the essence of what you're doing with the tools that you use.
确实 就绝对规模来说
And indeed, on some absolute scale of things,
我们对计算机科学的实质的了解
we probably know less about the essence of computer science
比埃及人对几何学的了解还少
than the ancient Egyptians really knew about geometry.
那么 我所谓的计算机科学的本质是什么呢
Well, what do I mean by the essence of computer science?
我所谓的几何学本质又是什么呢
What do I mean by the essence of geometry?
看 可以确认的是 古埃及人确实使用测量仪器
See, it's certainly true that these Egyptians went off
并且已经消失多年
and used surveying instruments,
但当我们在几千年后回过头来重新审视这段历史
but when we look back on them after a couple of thousand years,
我们会说
we say,
天啊 看他们在做什么
gee, what they were doing,
他们的工作是多么的重要
the important stuff they were doing,
已经开始对时间和空间进行形式化表述
was to begin to formalize notions about space and time,
并归纳出一套讨论数学真理的形式化方法
to start a way of talking about mathematical truths formally.
这直接导致了公理化方法
That led to the axiomatic method.
以及各种现代数学的产生
That led to sort of all of modern mathematics,
同时也指明了一种精确讨论
figuring out a way to talk precisely about
所谓的描述真理的陈述性知识的方法
so-called declarative knowledge, what is true.
与此相似的 我认为未来人们会回过头来审视并说
Well, similarly, I think in the future people will look back and say,
啊 这些20世纪的原始人
yes, those primitives in the 20th century were fiddling around
不务正业地玩弄着叫计算机的小玩意
with these gadgets called computers,
但它们真正在做的是开始学习
but really what they were doing is starting to learn
如何去对计算过程进行形式化表述
how to formalize intuitions about process,
如何去解决问题
how to do things,
并结合两者发展一套对问题处理过程精确表述的方法
starting to develop a way to talk precisely about how-to knowledge,
这与讨论真理的几何学形成了对照
as opposed to geometry that talks about what is true.
让我给你们举个例子吧
Let me give you an example of that.
来瞧瞧
Let's take a look
数学中是这样来定义平方根的:
Here is a piece of mathematics that says what a square root is.
定义X的平方根Y是这样一个数
The square root of X is the number Y,
Y的平方等于X 且Y大于等于0
such that Y squared is equal to X and Y is greater than 0.
这是一个很好的定义
Now, that's a fine piece of mathematics,
但它只告诉了你平方根是什么
but just telling you what a square root is
却没有告诉你如何去求取一个平方根
doesn't really say anything about how you might go out and find one.
那么我们将其与一条指令性知识做比较
So let's contrast that with a piece of imperative knowledge,
你如何去求取一个平方根
how you might go out and find a square root.
事实上 这来自于埃及 不太久远的埃及
This, in fact, also comes from Egypt, not ancient, ancient Egypt.
亚历山大的Heron提出的一个算法
This is an algorithm due to Heron of Alexandria,
称作连续取均值求平方根法
called how to find a square root by successive averaging.
这个算法是说
And what it says is that,
为了算出平方根
in order to find a square root,
首先你应该给出一个猜测值guess 并不断改进
you make a guess, you improve that guess --
改进的方法是通过
and the way you improve the guess
不断求猜测值guess与X/guess的平均值
is to average the guess and X over the guess,
我们稍后将会讨论
and we'll talk a little bit later about
为什么这是合理的
why that's a reasonable thing--
通过不断改进 直到它足够精确
and you keep improving the guess until it's good enough.
这就是实现方法
That's a method.
这也是如何完成一项工作与
That's how to do something as opposed to
其对应的陈述性知识的对照
declarative knowledge that says what you're looking for.
这就是一个过程
That's a process.
那么 通常来说什么是过程呢？
Well, what's a process in general?
这定义起来非常困难
It's kind of hard to say.
你可以将它象征性地看成一个活在计算机内
You can think of it as like a magical spirit
并且可以完成一些操作的精灵
that sort of lives in the computer and does something.
一些被称为程序的规则模式
And the thing that directs a process is
指导着这类过程的进行
a pattern of rules called a procedure.
程序可以被认为是符咒
So procedures are the spells, if you like,
使用程序来控制这些精灵完成一些操作就叫做过程
that control these magical spirits that are the processes.
你们知道人人都需要一门魔法语言
I guess you know everyone needs a magical language,
那些魔术师 真正的魔术师 用远古的阿卡狄亚语
and sorcerers, real sorcerers,
或者苏美尔语 或者巴比伦语 或者其它的
use ancient Arcadian or Sumerian or Babylonian or whatever.
而我们将用一门叫Lisp的魔法语言
We're going to conjure our spirits
来召唤出我们的精灵
in a magical language called Lisp,
这门语言是被设计用来
which is a language designed for talking about,
编写如咒语版的程序 来指导过程的进行
for casting the spells that are procedures to direct the processes.
学习Lisp非常容易
Now, it's very easy to learn Lisp.
事实上 我会在几分钟内教会你
In fact, in a few minutes, I'm going to teach you,
整个Lisp
essentially, all of Lisp.
及其所有的规则
I'm going to teach you, essentially, all of the rules.
你不必感到很惊讶
And you shouldn't find that particularly surprising.
这就像你在学习象棋时
That's sort of like saying it's very easy
认为象棋的规则十分简单一样
to learn the rules of chess.
事实也如此 几分钟内
And indeed, in a few minutes,
你可以与任何人谈论象棋的规则
you can tell somebody the rules of chess.
但是 这全然不等同于说
But of course, that's very different from
你所知道这些规则所蕴含的东西
saying you understand the implications of those rules
以及如何利用这些规则去成为象棋大师
and how to use those rules to become a masterful chess player.
Lisp也是如此
Well, Lisp is the same way.
我将在几分钟内道清规则
We're going to state the rules in a few minutes,
这说起来非常容易
and it'll be very easy to see.
但真正困难的是如何运用这些规则
But what's really hard is going to be the implications of those rules,
以及你如何利用这些规则成为编程大师
how you exploit those rules to be a master programmer.
这些规则的应用将占据我们
And the implications of those rules are going to take us the,
余下的课程 甚至更多
well, the whole rest of the subject and, of course, way beyond.
所以 在计算机科学中
OK, so in computer science,
我们的任务则是
we're in the business of
形式化这种如有关“怎么做”的指令性知识
formalizing this sort of how-to imperative knowledge,
并将之付诸实际
how to do stuff.
这也便是计算机科学的真正的议题
And the real issues of computer science are, of course,
当然 并不是告诉人们如何去求平方根
not telling people how to do square roots.
因为如果那是计算机科学的全部的的话
Because if that was all it was,
就不会有什么大问题了
there wouldn't be no big deal.
真正的问题来自于当我们尝试
The real problems come when we try to
构建非常非常大的系统时
build very, very large systems,
程序可能会长达数千页
computer programs that are thousands of pages long,
长得没有人能马上将其装入脑中
so long that nobody can really hold them in their heads all at once.
而使这些得以实现则是因为
And the only reason that that's possible is because
我们有在大系统中控制复杂度的技术
there are techniques for controlling the complexity of these large systems.
这些控制复杂度的技术
And these techniques that are controlling complexity
正是我们课程所讨论的
are what this course is really about.
从某种意义上来说
And in some sense,
这也正是计算机科学的关键所在
that's really what computer science is about.
这样说听起来或许很奇怪
Now, that may seem like a very strange thing to say.
毕竟 除了计算机科学家外
Because after all, a lot of people besides computer scientists
仍然有很多人在做复杂度控制相关的工作
deal with controlling complexity.
一个航班就是一个非常复杂的系统
A large airliner is an extremely complex system,
设计它的航空工程师
and the aeronautical engineers who design that
便在处理这个巨大的复杂度
are dealing with immense complexity.
但这种复杂度又与
But there's a difference between that kind of complexity
计算机科学中的（复杂度）有别
and what we deal with in computer science.
从某种意义上来说
And that is that computer science,
因为计算机科学不是“真实”的（译注：非物理系统的）
in some sense, isn't real.
例如 当一名工程师设计物理系统时
You see, when an engineer is designing a physical system,
这些都是由真实的物理部件构成
that's made out of real parts.
负责的该工作的工程师
The engineers who worry about that
就得对付系统中的公差、近似值以及噪声
have to address problems of tolerance and approximation and noise in the system.
譬如说 作为一名电气工程师
So for example, as an electrical engineer,
可以很容易的做一个单极放大器
I can go off and easily build a one-stage amplifier
或者是一个双极放大器
or a two-stage amplifier,
也可想象将其大量串联
and I can imagine cascading a lot of them
来建造一个百万极的放大器
to build a million-stage amplifier.
但这样做是不可行的
But it's ridiculous to build such a thing,
因为在远没到百万数量级的时候
because long before the millionth stage,
这种组合方法打从头产生的热噪声
the thermal noise in those components way at the beginning
会慢慢增强 并使得我们的幸苦付之一炬
is going to get amplified and make the whole thing meaningless.
计算机科学处理的是理想化组件
Computer science deals with idealized components.
我们对将要结合在一起的
We know as much as we want about these little program
程序和数据了如指掌
and data pieces that we're fitting things together.
我们不需要去关心公差
We don't have to worry about tolerance.
也就是说 在构建大系统时
And that means that, in building a large program,
在我理想和现实之间
there's not all that much difference
并不没有太大的不同
between what I can build and what I can imagine,
因为这些部分都是抽象单元
because the parts are these abstract entities
可以随心所欲的组合
that I know as much as I want.
可以据目前所知而自由构建
I know about them as precisely as I'd like.
就是与其它的工程不同之处
So as opposed to other kinds of engineering,
（在其它的工程中）对你所构建系统的约束
where the constraints on what you can build
来自于物理系统以及
are the constraints of physical systems,
物理定律 噪声 近似值等
the constraints of physics and noise and approximation,
而建立大型软件系统时所施加的约束
the constraints imposed in building large software systems
就是对我们大脑的限制
are the limitations of our own minds.
从这个角度来看
So in that sense,
计算机科学就像是工程中的一种抽象形式
computer science is like an abstract form of engineering.
在这种工程中 我们忽略
It's the kind of engineering where you ignore
现实所施加的约束
the constraints that are imposed by reality.
那么 这其中有哪些技术呢
Well, what are some of these techniques?
计算机科学中并没有特别的技术
They're not special to computer science.
第一个技术是在很多工程中都使用的
First technique, which is used in all of engineering,
被称为“黑盒抽象”的方法
is a kind of abstraction called black-box abstraction.
即将一些东西组合并封装起来
Take something and build a box about it.
以之前我们提到的求取平方根的方法为例
Let's see, for example, if we looked at that square root method,
我将这些操作视为一个“盒子”
I might want to take that and build a box.
也就是说 为了找到X的平方根
That sort of says, to find the square root of X.
或许会有一系列的复杂规则
And that might be a whole complicated set of rules.
我们将规则封装 给定输入数据即可获取结果
And that might end up being a kind of thing where I can put in,
比如说 输入36 然后说36的平方根是多少呢
say, 36 and say, what's the square root of 36?
则给出结果 6
And out comes 6.
重点是
And the important thing is that
通过这样的设计
I'd like to design that so that
可以方便他人的使用
if George comes along and would like to compute,
例如Goerge想计算A的平方根加上B的平方根
say, the square root of A plus the square root of B,
他无需了解“盒子”内部的构成
he can take this thing and use it as a module
而直接可以以模块的形式使用它
without having to look inside
也可以利用它去构建新的“盒子”
and build something that looks like this,
例如构建一个 A和B以及一个平方根和或者另一个平方根盒子
like an A and a B and a square root box and another square root box
然后将这些结果加在一起并输出答案
and then something that adds that would put out the answer.
如你所见 就我想实现的功能的层面来看
And you can see, just from the fact that I want to do that,
对于George来说
is from George's point of view,
盒子内部是什么样并不重要
the internals of what's in here should not be important.
例如 以下这些说法都没什么问题
So for instance, it shouldn't matter that, when I wrote this,
我说求X的平方根
I said I want to find the square root of X.
也可以说计算Y的平方根
I could have said the square root of Y,
或者其它任何数的平方根
or the square root of A, or anything at all
黑盒抽象的基本规则是
That's the fundamental notion of putting something in a box
将处理过程放入盒子里以隐藏细节
using black-box abstraction to suppress detail.
这样做的原因则是你可以脱身去构建更大的盒子
And the reason for that is you want to go off and build bigger boxes.
现在 除了隐藏细节外
Now, there's another reason for doing black-box abstraction
使用黑盒抽象还有另外一个原因
other than you want to suppress detail for building bigger boxes.
有的时候 你想要用
Sometimes you want to say that your way of doing something,
你的方式去完成一件事
your how-to method,
这是常有的事儿
is an instance of a more general thing,
同时 你也希望你的表述方式能够具有普遍性
and you'd like your language to be able to express that generality.
我们接着用实例来说明
Let me show you another example
继续刚才关于平方根的讨论
sticking with square roots.
让我们回过头再来看看
Let's go back and take another look at that slide
求平方根的算法
with the square root algorithm on it.
想一想之前是怎么说的
Remember what that says.
为了求解 首先要作出猜测
That says, in order to do something, I make a guess,
然后基于这个猜测 做出持续不断的改进
and I improve that guess, and I sort of keep improving that guess.
因此就存在一个找到某个到结果的通用方法
So there's the general strategy of, I'm looking for something,
就是持续不断地改进结果
and the way I find it is that I keep improving it.
这个例子 则可以做为找到某个结果的不动点
Now, that's a particular case of another kind of strategy
策略的特例
for finding a fixed point of something.
每个函数都有一个不动点
So you have a fixed point of a function.
函数的不动点是一个值
A fixed point of a function is something, is a value.
F的不动点Y满足F(Y)=Y
A fixed point of a function F is a value Y, such that F of Y equals Y.
首先要做是做出一个猜测
And the way I might do that is start with a guess.
在迭代函数F时不会改变的东西则是我们所求的结果
And then if I want something that doesn't change when I keep applying F,
我会不断迭代函数F直到结果不会有很大改变
is I'll keep applying F over and over until that result doesn't change very much.
这就是一个通法
So there's a general strategy.
因此 为了计算X的平方根
And then, for example, to compute the square root of X,
我可以试着找到Y与X/Y的平均值函数的不动点
I can try and find a fixed point of the function which takes Y to the average of X/Y.
因为如果我真有一个等于X平方根的Y
And the idea that is that if I really had Y equal to the square root of X,
那么Y和X/Y应为同一值
then Y and X/Y would be the same value.
它们俩都是X的平方根
They'd both be the square root of X,
因为X除根号X得根号X
because X over the square root of X is the square root of X.
如果平均值Y等于X的平方根
And so the average if Y were equal to the square of X,
那么这个平均值就不会改变
then the average wouldn't change.
因此X的平方根即是某一特定函数的不动点
So the square root of X is a fixed point of that particular function.
现在 我将要描述
Now, what I'd like to have, I'd like to express
寻找不动点的通用方法
the general strategy for finding fixed points.
我所希望做的就是
So what I might imagine doing, is to find,
用我自己的语言定义一个可以获得不动点的“盒子”
is to be able to use my language to define a box that says "fixed point,"
正如我可以定义一个输出平方根的盒子一样
just like I could make a box that says "square root."
我想要用自己的语言来表述
And I'd like to be able to express this in my language.
因此 对于这种“怎么做”的指令性知识
So I'd like to express not only the imperative how-to knowledge
我不仅是想表达具体应该如何求平方根
of a particular thing like square root,
我也希望能够表述更加通用问题
but I'd like to be able to express the imperative knowledge
例如 怎么求取不动点
of how to do a general thing like how to find fixed point.
让我们再回过头来看看之前的幻灯片
And in fact, let's go back and look at that slide again.
不但如何去求取一个不动点
See, not only is this a piece of imperative knowledge,
是一种指令性知识
how to find a fixed point,
在这下面  这里
but over here on the bottom,
这儿还有另一种指令性知识 说的是
there's another piece of imperative knowledge which says,
计算平方根的一种方法就是应用找不动点的方法
one way to compute square root is to apply this general fixed point method.
如果 也想要表述这种指令性知识
So I'd like to also be able to express that imperative knowledge.
那结果会是什么样呢？
What would that look like?
这个不动点盒子可能会是这样
That would say, this fixed point box is such that
如果我输入一个函数 该函数从Y映射到Y和X/Y的平均值
if I input to it the function that takes Y to the average of Y and X/Y,
然后我们将会得到求不动点的盒子就是求平方根的一个方法
then what should come out of that fixed point box is a method for finding square roots.
因此在这些我们构建的盒子中
So in these boxes we're building,
输入和输出都不局限于数字
we're not only building boxes that you input numbers and output numbers,
我们将要构建能够
we're going to be building in boxes that,
找到平方根计算方法的盒子
in effect, compute methods like finding square root.
我用的是一个输入函数
And my take is their inputs functions,
比如Y映射到Y和X/Y的平均值的函数
like Y goes to the average of Y and X/Y.
我们之所以采用这种方式是希望
The reason we want to do that,
输入是一个过程 输出也是一个过程
the reason this is a procedure, will end up being a procedure,
处理过程中产生的值也是一个过程
as we'll see, whose value is another procedure,
之所以这样做是因为
the reason we want to do that is because
我们将通过程序来讨论指令性知识
procedures are going to be our ways of talking about imperative knowledge.
这种处理方式很强大
And the way to make that very powerful is
我们将可以基于此来讨论其它类型的知识
to be able to talk about other kinds of knowledge.
实际上 我们讨论的是一种生成过程的过程
So here is a procedure that, in effect, talks about another procedure,
一种生成通法的通法
a general strategy that itself talks about general strategies.
那么 我们将主要讨论三个主题的内容
Well, our first topic in this course--
而首个主题则是
there'll be three major topics--
黑盒抽象
will be black-box abstraction.
让我们稍稍深入一点
Let's look at that in a little bit more detail.
我们将讨论
What we're going to do is we will start out talking about
Lisp是如何通过基本对象建立起来的
how Lisp is built up out of primitive objects.
以及Lisp的构成
What does the language supply with us?
接下来 将会涉及到一些基本过程和基础数据
And we'll see that there are primitive procedures and primitive data.
然后我们将会看到
Then we're going to see,
我们如何使用这些基本对象
how do you take those primitives and
并把它们组合起来构建更复杂的东西
combine them to make more complicated things,
及相应的组合方法
means of combination?
后续将讨论各种进行组合的方法以及
And what we'll see is that there are ways of putting things together,
如何用基本过程来构建更复杂的过程
putting primitive procedures together to make more complicated procedures.
同时 我们也将看到如何将基本数据组合成复合数据
And we'll see how to put primitive data together to make compound data.
然后我们将会介绍如何对复合数据
Then we'll say, well, having made those compounds things,
如何将它们抽象出来
how do you abstract them?
如何用黑盒对它们进行封装
How do you put those black boxes around them
使得你可以将它们作为组件用于更复杂的东西
so you can use them as components in more complex things?
我们会发现这些都是通过定义程序
And we'll see that's done by defining procedures and
以及一种处理复合数据的数据抽象技术完成的
a technique for dealing with compound data called data abstraction.
最重要的是
And then, what's maybe the most important thing,
我们可以从中了解到专家是如何工作的
is going from just the rules to how does an expert work?
对于找不动点的方法来讲
How do you express common patterns of doing things, like saying, well,
找平方根的方式是它的一个特例
there's a general method of fixed point and
你如何表述完成工作中所存在的通用模式呢？
square root is a particular case of that?
我们将会使用
And we're going to use--
之前已经提到过的
I've already hinted at it--
某种叫做高阶过程的东西
something called higher-order procedures,
也就是说 它的输入输出和它本身都是过程
namely procedures whose inputs and outputs are themselves procedures.
我们将会看到一些有趣的东西
And then we'll also see something very interesting.
随着学习的深入 将会越发抽象
We'll see, as we go further and further on and become more abstract,
那么将会发现
there'll be very--
我们认为是数据和我们认为是过程之间的
well, the line between what we consider to be data and
分界线将变得模糊到难以置信的程度
what we consider to be procedures is going to blur at an incredible rate.
这便是我们的第一个主题 黑盒抽象
Well, that's our first subject, black-box abstraction.
让我们来看看第二个主题
Let's look at the second topic.
这样说吧
I can introduce it like this.
假设我想表达某个想法
See, suppose I want to express the idea--
请注意 我们讨论的是想法
remember, we're talking about ideas--
比如说
suppose I want to express the idea that
我想将某个元素与另两个元素之和相乘
I can take something and multiply it by the sum of two other things.
举例来说
So for example, I might say,
我用1和3（之和）乘2 得8
if I had 1 and 3 and multiply that by 2, I get 8.
但我这里想讨论的是关于线性组合的基本想法
But I'm talking about the general idea of what's called linear combination,
是说你可以将两个元素的和乘以另一个元素
that you can add two things and multiply them by something else.
在数集内思考这个问题是很容易的
It's very easy when I think about it for numbers,
但假设我想将这个想法应用于
but suppose I also want to use that same idea to think about,
对两向量a1和a2相加
I could add two vectors, a1 and a2,
乘以某一因子x然后得到另一向量
and then scale them by some factor x and get another vector.
我甚至可以说 若a1和a2皆为多项式
Or I might say, I want to think about a1 and a2 as being polynomials,
我想对这两个多项式求和
and I might want to add those two polynomials and
然后乘以2得到一个多项式
then multiply them by 2 to get a more complicated one.
同理 a1或a2也可以是电信号
Or a1 and a2 might be electrical signals,
我想将二个信号加和
and I might want to think about summing those two electrical signals and
并将结果放入一个放大器
then putting the whole thing through an amplifier,
用一个类似于2的因子乘以它们
multiplying it by some factor of 2 or something.
这种想法的基本点是 我希望用一个通用记号表示它们
The idea is I want to think about the general notion of that.
假如我们的语言可以很好的表述这类想法
Now, if our language is going to be good language for expressing those kind of general ideas,
如果真可以这样的话
if I really, really can do that,
我将会以这样的方式表述
I'd like to be able to say
用x乘以a1和a2的和
I'm going to multiply by x the sum of a1 and a2,
更进一步 我希望做更抽象更基本的表述
and I'd like that to express the general idea of
使其可以适应各个不同类型的a1和a2
all different kinds of things that a1 and a2 could be.
现在回过头来想想 似乎有点问题
Now, if you think about that, there's a problem,
毕竟 对两个数字和两个多项式进行加和运算
because after all, the actual primitive operations
所用的基本操作
that go on in the machine are obviously going to be different
在机器内部显然是不同的
if I'm adding two numbers than if I'm adding two polynomials,
对两个电信号或声波加和也有同样的问题
or if I'm adding the representation of two electrical signals or wave forms.
无论怎样 对不同类型的元素进行求和运算
Somewhere, there has to be the knowledge of the kinds of various things
总是需要使用不同的方法
that you can add and the ways of adding them.
现在 为了构建这样一个系统
Now, to construct such a system,
我们将如何使用这些知识呢？
the question is, where do I put that knowledge?
如何在各种方法中进行选择？
How do I think about the different kinds of choices I have?
而如果明天George又想出了一种新类型的对象
And if tomorrow George comes up with a new kind of object
并将它用于加和以及乘积
that might be added and multiplied,
我又该如何把这个新类型引入到系统中
how do I add George's new object to the system
而且能够做到不把已有的系统弄得一团糟？
without screwing up everything that was already there?
这便是我们的第二大主题
Well, that's going to be the second big topic,
控制复杂度的方法
the way of controlling that kind of complexity.
我们实现的方法是按照约定来实现相应的接口
And the way you do that is by establishing conventional interfaces,
并以此将各部分组合起来
agreed upon ways of plugging things together.
就如同电气工程中
Just like in electrical engineering,
人们为连接器规定标准阻抗
people have standard impedances for connectors,
如果用符合这个标准的东西来构建系统
and then you know if you build something with one of those standard impedances,
你就知道你可以把各个部件组合在一起
you can plug it together with something else.
这就是我们将要讨论的第二个主题：约定接口
So that's going to be our second large topic, conventional interfaces.
如我之前提到的
What we're going to see is, first, we're going to talk about the problem of generic operations,
接下来我们将讨论通用操作中的问题
which is the one I alluded to,
例如对各种不同类型数据进行均适用的加法操作
things like "plus" that have to work with all different kinds of data.
随后则会讨论通用操作
So we talk about generic operations.
然后我们将讨论大型架构问题
Then we're going to talk about really large-scale structures.
如果通过对现实世界的复杂系统建模
How do you put together very large programs
来构建大型程序
that model the kinds of complex systems in the real world that you'd like to model?
我们将看到 在构建这样的系统时
And what we're going to see is that
有两种非常重要的方法
there are two very important metaphors for putting together such systems.
其一是面向对象编程
One is called object-oriented programming,
在这种模式中 你把你的系统想象成一个社区
where you sort of think of your system as a kind of society
社区中的各个部分都是通过相互间传递消息联系起来的
full of little things that interact by sending information between them.
其二是关于聚集的操作 称作“流”
And then the second one is operations on aggregates, called streams,
使用这种方式构建大型系统
where you think of a large system put together kind of
类似于电气工程师构造大型电气系统
like a signal processing engineer puts together a large electrical system.
这就是我们的第二个话题
That's going to be our second topic.
现在 我们将要讨论第三个话题
Now, the third thing we're going to come to,
控制复杂度的第三个技术
the third basic technique for controlling complexity,
便是定义新的语言
is making new languages.
因为有时 当你有点受不了设计的复杂度时
Because sometimes, when you're sort of overwhelmed by the complexity of a design,
你可以通过定义一门新的语言来控制系统复杂度
the way that you control that complexity is to pick a new design language.
新语言的设计意图是为了强调系统的某个方面
And the purpose of the new design language will be to highlight different aspects of the system.
它一方面隐藏了部分细节 另一方面则但强调一些其他的细节
It will suppress some kinds of details and emphasize other kinds of details.
这部分将是课程中最神奇的部分
This is going to be the most magical part of the course.
我们将开始于构建新的计算机语言
We're going to start out by actually looking at the technology for building new computer languages.
实际上我们首先要完成的工作已经内建于Lisp之中了
The first thing we're going to do is actually build in Lisp.
我们将展现如何用Lisp来解释Lisp
We're going to express in Lisp the process of interpreting Lisp itself.
这是一个非常类似于自循环的过程
And that's going to be a very sort of self-circular thing.
这与（Lisp中）一个神奇的符号有关
There's a little mystical symbol that has to do with that.
解释Lisp的步骤是
The process of interpreting Lisp is sort of a giant wheel of two processes,
应用和求值——这两大步骤的轮转
apply and eval,
这两者不断地互相交替进行
which sort of constantly reduce expressions to each other.
接下来 我们将看到其余神奇的东西
Then we're going to see all sorts of other magical things.
譬如另一种魔法符号
Here's another magical symbol.
一种叫做Y运算符的东西
This is sort of the Y operator,
某种意义上 它在过程式语言中用于 表达无限
which is, in some sense, the expression of infinity inside our procedural language.
我们也会谈论到它
We'll take a look at that.
总之 这部分课程被称作“元语言抽象”
In any case, this section of the course is called Metalinguistic Abstraction,
主要讨论如何构建一门新语言
abstracting by talking about how you construct new languages.
如我所言 我们将从了解解释的过程开始
As I said, we're going to start out by looking at the process of interpretation.
随后则一起讨论应用-求值循环和构建Lisp
We're going to look at this apply-eval loop, and build Lisp.
你将发现这种方法具有相当的普遍性
Then, just to show you that this is very general,
我们将用同样的技术去构建一门全完不同的语言
we're going to use exactly the same technology to build a very different kind of language,
一种所谓的逻辑编程语言
a so-called logic programming language,
一种无关具有输入和输出的过程
where you don't really talk about procedures at all that have inputs and outputs.
而仅关注元素之间关系的语言
What you do is talk about relations between things.
最终 我们将讨论如何将这些东西
And then finally, we're going to talk about how you implement these things very concretely
实实在在的实现在简单的机器上
on the very simplest kind of machines.
比如说这个
We'll see something like this.
如图所示的芯片
This is a picture of a chip,
就是我们在硬件部分谈及的Lisp解释器
which is the Lisp interpreter that we will be talking about then in hardware.
这三大主题就是本课的提纲
Well, there's an outline of the course, three big topics.
黑盒抽象 约定接口 元语言抽象
Black-box abstraction, conventional interfaces, metalinguistic abstraction.
好 先休息一会儿 然后正式开始
Now, let's take a break now and then we'll get started.
[音乐]
[JESU, JOY OF MAN'S DESIRING]
现在让我们正式开始学习Lisp
Let's actually start in learning Lisp now.
事实上 我们将开始学习一些非常重要的内容
Actually, we'll start out by learning something much more important,
在这门课程中最重要的 不是Lisp本身
maybe the very most important thing in this course, which is not Lisp,
而是一种的通用框架体系
in particular, of course, but rather a general framework
我们用它来组织我之前提到的语言
for thinking about languages that I already alluded to.
当有人要向你展示一门新语言
When somebody tells you they're going to show you a language,
你应该问他
what you should say is,
（构成语言的）基本元素有哪些？
what I'd like you to tell me is what are the primitive elements?
这门语言使用哪些基本元素？
What does the language come with?
你是如何将这些元素组合在一起的？
Then, what are the ways you put those together?
组合的方法是什么？
What are the means of combination?
允许你将这些基本元素整合在一起
What are the things that allow you to take these primitive elements
以构建更大的对象的又是什么？
and build bigger things out of them?
把东西构建在一起的方法是什么？
What are the ways of putting things together?
以及 抽象的方法是什么？
And then, what are the means of abstraction?
我们如何利用这些元素并把它们封装成盒子？
How do we take those complicated things and draw those boxes around them?
我们如何为它们命名使得我们可以
How do we name them so that we can now use them
把它们当作基本元素来用于构建更复杂的东西？
as if they were primitive elements in making still more complex things?
等等 等等 等等
And so on, and so on, and so on.
因此 当有人告诉你
So when someone says to you, gee,
嘿 我发明了一种新的计算机语言
I have a great new computer language,
你不应该问 用你的语言编写求逆矩阵需要多少代码
you don't say, how many characters does it take to invert a matrix?
这是风马牛不相及的
It's irrelevant.
如果该语言没有内建了矩阵或者类似的东西
What you say is, if the language did not come with matrices built in
那你就应该问他
or with something else built in,
应该如何构建矩阵？
how could I then build that thing?
如何通过组合来构建？
What are the means of combination which would allow me to do that?
如何对其进行抽象
And then, what are the means of abstraction
把它作为基本元素
which allow me then to use those as elements
来构建更复杂的东西？
in making more complicated things yet?
我们将了解到Lisp的一些基本数据和基本过程
Well, we're going to see that Lisp has some primitive data and some primitive procedures.
好吧 这次是真的开始了
In fact, let's really start.
这里有一个Lisp的基本数据 数字3
And here's a piece of primitive data in Lisp, number 3.
事实上 如果打破沙锅问到底的话 这不是数字3
Actually, if I'm being very pedantic, that's not the number 3.
这只是一个符号 用以代表柏拉图观念下的数字3的
That's some symbol that represents Plato's concept of the number 3.
这又是另一个
And here's another.
这个是Lisp中又一个基本数据 17.4
Here's some more primitive data in Lisp, 17.4.
又或者说 代表17.4
Or actually, some representation of 17.4.
这儿还有一个5
And here's another one, 5.
然后这儿又有一个内建于Lisp的基本对象“+”
Here's another primitive object that's built in Lisp, addition.
如果又要继续深究的话
Actually, to use the same kind of pedantic--
这只是一个名字 代表对元素进行加和的基本方法而已
this is a name for the primitive method of adding things.
就像这个是柏拉图式的3
Just like this is a name for Plato's number 3,
这也只是一个代表柏拉图观念下的将某些元素加和起来
this is a name for Plato's concept of how you add things.
这些都是基本元素
So those are some primitive elements.
我可以将它们放在一起
I can put them together.
我可以说 3加17.4加5的和是多少
I can say, gee, what's the sum of 3 and 17.4 and 5?
这等同于说
And the way I do that is to say,
让我们把求和运算符应用于这三个数
let's apply the sum operator to these three numbers.
我可以得到什么呢 是8 是17 还是25.4
And I should get, what? 8, 17. 25.4.
因此 我可以问Lisp这个的值是多少
So I should be able to ask Lisp what the value of this is,
（表达式）返回25.4
and it will return 25.4.
介绍一些术语吧
Let's introduce some names.
我所写的这些东西就叫做组合式
This thing that I typed is called a combination.
通常 一个组合式是由运算符
And a combination consists, in general, of applying an operator--
这些就是运算符
so this is an operator--
和应用该运算符的运算对象组成
to some operands.
这些是运算对象
These are the operands.
当然 我可以完成更复杂的事
And of course, I can make more complex things.
我可以使之更复杂是因为 这些运算对象
The reason I can get complexity out of this is because the operands themselves,
通常来说 也可以是组合式
in general, can be combinations.
比如 3加上5乘以6乘以8乘以2的积的和是多少
So for instance, I could say, what is the sum of 3 and the product of 5 and 6 and 8 and 2?
而我应该得到 我算一下 30 40 43
And I should get-- let's see-- 30, 40, 43.
因此Lisp会返回这个表达式的值是43
So Lisp should tell me that that's 43.
后续我们将看到构造组合式是组合的基本需求
Forming combinations is the basic needs of combination that we'll be looking at.
你所看到的这些语法
And then, well, you see some syntax here.
就是Lisp用的所谓的前缀表示法
Lisp uses what's called prefix notation,
意即操作符在操作数的左端
which means that the operator is written to the left of the operands.
这只是个约定
It's just a convention.
注意 这些都被括起来了
And notice, it's fully parenthesized.
这些括号使得它们区别开来
And the parentheses make it completely unambiguous.
因此只要看看这个 我就可以知道这个是运算符
So by looking at this, I can see that there's the operator,
以及这有1个 2个 3个 4个运算对象
and there are 1, 2, 3, 4 operands.
而且我也可以发现第二个运算对象是个组合式
And I can see that the second operand here is itself some combination
该组合式有一个运算符和两个运算对象
that has one operator and two operands.
Lisp中的括号 有点或者非常不同于
Parentheses in Lisp are a little bit,
通常数学中的括号
or are very unlike parentheses in conventional mathematics.
数学中 我们常将其用于分组
In mathematics, we sort of use them to mean grouping,
如果有时你忘了闭合括号 但其他人能理解你的意图
and it sort of doesn't hurt if sometimes you leave out parentheses
这也无关紧要
if people understand that that's a group.
通常的 你多加了括号也无所谓
And in general, it doesn't hurt if you put in extra parentheses,
因为这样只会使得分组更加明确
because that maybe makes the grouping more distinct.
Lisp可不像这样
Lisp is not like that.
Lisp中你既不能不闭合括号
In Lisp, you cannot leave out parentheses,
亦不能添加多余的括号
and you cannot put in extra parentheses,
因为加括号总是意味着
because putting in parentheses always means,
确切的来说 所括之物是一个组合式
exactly and precisely, this is a combination which has meaning,
表示将运算符应用于运算对象
applying operators to operands.
如果我不闭合这个括号
And if I left this out, if I left those parentheses out,
这个就变成其它的意思了
it would mean something else.
事实上 我们可以这么来理解这个问题
In fact, the way to think about this,
把我写的这些东西想作一个树
is really what I'm doing when I write something like this is writing a tree.
这个组合式实际上是一个树 树具有一个“+”
So this combination is a tree that has a plus and
以及 一个3和一些其它的东西和一个8 还有一个2
then a 3 and then a something else and an 8 and a 2.
而这里的其它的东西
And then this something else here is
它本身是一个有一个“*”一个5和一个6的子树
itself a little subtree that has a star and a 5 and a 6.
我们可以这样认为
And the way to think of that is, really,
我们只是在构建这些树而已
what's going on are we're writing these trees,
括号只是将这种二维结构写作线性字符串
and parentheses are just a way to write this two-dimensional structure
的一种方法罢了
as a linear character string.
因为至少在Lisp发明时 人们还在用电传打字机或者打孔卡
Because at least when Lisp first started and people had teletypes or punch cards or whatever,
这种记法方便多了
this was more convenient.
如果Lisp是在当下被发明的 语法可能会像树那样
Maybe if Lisp started today, the syntax of Lisp would look like that.
那么 让我们看看在计算机里面它究竟是什么样
Well, let's look at what that actually looks like on the computer.
这里有个Lisp解释套件
Here I have a Lisp interaction set up.
这是个编辑器
There's a editor.
我将要在上方写一些表达式并让Lisp对其求值
And on the top, I'm going to type some values and ask Lisp what they are.
比如 我可以问Lisp
So for instance, I can say to Lisp,
这个符号的值是多少
what's the value of that symbol?
我键入3
That's 3.
然后叫Lisp对其求值
And I ask Lisp to evaluate it.
然后你就会看到Lisp在下面返回了一些信息
And there you see Lisp has returned on the bottom,
这个值就是3
and said, oh yeah, that's 3.
我也可以问 3加上4加上8的和是多少
Or I can say, what's the sum of 3 and 4 and 8?
键入这个组合式
What's that combination?
让Lisp对其求值
And ask Lisp to evaluate it.
返回15
That's 15.
我可以键入一些更复杂的东西
Or I can type in something more complicated.
将3乘以7加19.5的和的乘积求和得多少
I can say, what's the sum of the product of 3 and the sum of 7 and 19.5?
你会发现Lisp内建了一些功能
And you'll notice here that Lisp has something built in
帮你跟踪这些括号
that helps me keep track of all these parentheses.
看我键入下一个右圆括号
Watch as I type the next closed parentheses,
用于闭合以“*”开头的那个组合式
which is going to close the combination starting with the star.
开头的那个左括号会闪一下
The opening one will flash.
我把这些括号擦去 再示范一次
Here, I'll rub those out and do it again.
键入右括号 闭合了“+”组合式
Type close, and you see that closes the plus.
再键入右括号 闭合了“*”组合式
Close again, that closes the star.
现在我又回到了加 我将它们与4相加
Now I'm back to the sum, and maybe I'm going to add that all to 4.
闭合了“+”组合式
That closes the plus.
现在我补全了组合式 然后我问Lisp它们的值是多少
Now I have a complete combination, and I can ask Lisp for the value of that.
这种内建于各种Lisp系统的
That kind of paren balancing is something that's built into
括号匹配工具帮你跟进（括号匹配）
a lot of Lisp systems to help you keep track,
因为手工闭合这些括号太辛苦了
because it is kind of hard just by hand doing all these parentheses.
这又是另外一种保持括号跟进的约定
There's another kind of convention for keeping track of parentheses.
我另外写一个复杂的组合式
Let me write another complicated combination.
将3和5的积与某个元素求和
Let's take the sum of the product of 3 and 5 and add that to something.
现在我将要缩进
And now what I'm going to do is
使得这些运算对象都是垂直书写的
I'm going to indent so that the operands are written vertically.
将这些加上47乘以
Which the sum of that and the product of 47 and--
恩…… 47乘以20和6.8的差
let's say the product of 47 with a difference of 20 and 6.8.
意即从20中减去6.8
That means subtract 6.8 from 20.
然后 这个括号闭合了
And then you see the parentheses close.
闭合“-” 闭合“*”
Close the minus. Close the star.
现在 我们再写一个运算符
And now let's get another operator.
Lisp编辑器自动缩进到正确的位置
You see the Lisp editor here is indenting to the right position automatically
来帮助我保持跟进
to help me keep track.
我再示范一次
I'll do that again.
这样就又闭合了最后一个括号
I'll close that last parentheses again.
它匹配了这个“+”（的括号）
You see it balances the plus.
现在我想问 这个的值是多少
Now I can say, what's the value of that?
因此 这两件事 缩进到正确的位置
So those two things, indenting to the right level,
也就是所谓的美观的输出
which is called pretty printing,
以及闭合提示
and flashing parentheses,
是许多Lisp系统所内建用于帮你保持跟进的工具
are two things that a lot of Lisp systems have built in to help you keep track.
你应该学习如何使用它们
And you should learn how to use them.
好 这些都是基本的内容
Ok, those are the primitives.
这就是一种组合的方法
There's a means of combination.
现在让我们来看看抽象的方法
Now let's go up to the means of abstraction.
我希望我能够写一些像这样的组合式
I'd like to be able to take the idea that I do some combination like this,
将它抽象化并给它命名
and abstract it and give it a simple name,
使得我可以将其作为一个（我们语言的）元素
so I can use that as an element.
在Lisp中 我可以用“define”来实现
And I do that in Lisp with "define."
比如说
So I can say, for example,
定义A为5乘以5
define A to be the product of 5 and 5.
现在我可以问Lisp
And now I could say, for example, to Lisp,
A和A的乘积是多少
what is the product of A and A?
这个是25所以这个就是625
And this should be 25, and this should be 625.
但更重要的则是 我现在可以使用A
And then, crucial thing, I can now use A--
我已经在这个组合式里面用过了
here I've used it in a combination--
但我也可以在更复杂的组合式里面使用它
but I could use that in other more complicated things that I name in turn.
我也可以说 定义B为
So I could say, define B to be the sum of,
A与5乘以A的积的和
we'll say, A and the product of 5 and A.
闭合“+”
And then close the plus.
让我们来看看它在计算机中是怎样的吧
Let's take a look at that on the computer and see how that looks.
我就像黑板上写的那样键入就可以了
So I'll just type what I wrote on the board.
我告诉Lisp
I could say, define A to be the product of 5 and 5.
定义A为5乘以5的积
And I'll tell that to Lisp.
注意Lisp在下方回应了一个A
And notice what Lisp responded there with was an A in the bottom.
通常来说 你如果在Lisp中键入了一个定义
In general, when you type in a definition in Lisp,
它返回被定义的符号
it responds with the symbol being defined.
现在我问Lisp A乘以A的积是多少
Now I could say to Lisp, what is the product of A and A?
Lisp返回625
And it says that's 625.
我也可以定义B为A加上5乘以A的积的和
I can define B to be the sum of A and the product of 5 and A.
闭合“*” 闭合“+” 闭合“define”
Close a paren closes the star.  Close the plus. Close the "define."
Lisp在下方正常返回B
Lisp says, OK, B, there on the bottom.
现在我可以问Lisp B的值是多少
And now I can say to Lisp, what's the value of B?
我也可以问一些更复杂的事
And I can say something more complicated,
比如A加上B除以5的商的和是多少
like what's the sum of A and the quotient of B and 5?
这个“/”是另一个基本运算符 代表除
That slash is divide, another primitive operator.
我让B除以5 并加在A上
I've divided B by 5, added it to A.
Lisp正常返回55
Lisp says, OK, that's 55.
就像这样
So there's what it looks like.
这是定义东西的基本方法
There's the basic means of defining something.
这是最简单的命名方法 但并不是很强大
It's the simplest kind of naming, but it's not really very powerful.
注意我们讨论的是通用方法
See, what I'd really like to name--
因此我真正想定义的是
remember, we're talking about general methods--
一种通用方法 可以
I'd like to name, oh, the general idea that, for example,
得到 5乘5 6乘6 1001乘1001 1001.7乘1001.7
I could multiply 5 by 5, or 6 by 6, or 1,001 by 1,001, 1,001.7 by 1,001.7.
我想给一个数与其自身相乘这种想法一个名字
I'd like to be able to name the general idea of multiplying something by itself.
你应该知道 这叫做平方
Well, you know what that is. That's called squaring.
而在Lisp中我应该这样实现
And the way I can do that in Lisp is I can say,
定义 square某个叫x的东西 为 将x乘以x自己
define to square something x, multiply x by itself.
定义完毕后 我可以问Lisp
And then having done that, I could say to Lisp,
比如 10的平方是多少
for example, what's the square of 10?
Lisp返回100
And Lisp will say 100.
让我们深入讨论一下
So now let's actually look at that a little more closely.
这儿是square的定义
Right, there's the definition of square.
square某个元素 即是将该元素进行自乘
To square something, multiply it by itself.
这里的x
You see this x here.
应该算是一种代词
That x is kind of a pronoun,
指代了我要做平方的元素
which is the something that I'm going to square.
实际上我将其乘以x 即是乘以它自己
And what I do with it is I multiply x, I multiply it by itself.
这些就是定义一个过程的记法
OK. So there's the notation for defining a procedure.
这样说可能把你搞糊涂了
Actually, this is a little bit confusing,
因为这就像我在用square一样
because this is sort of how I might use square.
但如果我说x的平方根或者10的平方根
And I say square root of x or square root of 10,
并没有说清楚我对什么做了定义
but it's not making it very clear that I'm actually naming something.
所以让我换个方式来进行定义
So let me write this definition in another way
这样可以清楚的看到定义的具体内容
that makes it a little bit more clear that I'm naming something.
我“定义”square为(lambda (x) (* x x))
I'll say, "define" square to be lambda of x times xx.
这里 我定义 square 就像我某命名为A一样
Here, I'm naming something square, just like over here, I'm naming something A.
我定义square
The thing that I'm naming square--
这里 我把这个组合式的值命名为A
here, the thing I named A was the value of this combination.
在这里 我把这个东西命名为square
Here, the thing that I'm naming square is this thing
以lambda开头
that begins with lambda,
lambda在Lisp中用以构建一个过程
and lambda is Lisp's way of saying make a procedure.
请仔细看一下幻灯片上的内容
Let's look at that more closely on the slide.
这个定义读作
The way I read that definition is to say,
将square定义为一个由
I define square to be make a procedure--
lambda构造的
that's what the lambda is--
一个有带有参数x的过程
make a procedure with an argument named x.
而该过程返回将x自乘的结果
And what it does is return the results of multiplying x by itself.
一般来讲 这是最佳的定义方式
Now, in general, we're going to be using this top form of defining,
因为这个更加方便一点
just because it's a little bit more convenient.
但是也别忘了它实质上也是这个
But don't lose sight of the fact that it's really this.
事实上 就Lisp解释器而言
In fact, as far as the Lisp interpreter's concerned,
这两种方法没有区别
there's no difference between typing this to it and typing this to it.
换句话说 这只是一种语法糖
And there's a word for that, sort of syntactic sugar.
语法糖的意思就是
What syntactic sugar means,
这种形式输入更方便一些
it's having somewhat more convenient surface forms for typing something.
这只是这下面的有lambda的表达式的语法糖而已
So this is just really syntactic sugar for this underlying Greek thing with the lambda.
你应该记住
And the reason you should remember that is don't forget that,
当我这样写的时候 其实是在对某个东西进行命名
when I write something like this, I'm really naming something.
我将其命名为square
I'm naming something square,
square 代表构建一个过程
and the something that I'm naming square is a procedure that's getting constructed.
让我们看看在计算机里面又是 怎样的吧
Well, let's look at that on the computer, too.
定义(square x)为x乘以x的积
So I'll come and I'll say, define square of x to be times xx.
将它送入Lisp
Now I'll tell Lisp that.
返回square
It says "square."
现在 我已经将某个东西命名为square了
See, I've named something "square."
完毕后 我就可以问Lisp 1001的平方是多少
Now, having done that, I can ask Lisp for, what's the square of 1,001?
或者更通常的来说 我可以问 5加上7的和的平方是多少
Or in general, I could say, what's the square of the sum of 5 and 7?
12的平方是144
The square of 12's 144.
在某些组合式中我亦可把square当作一个元素
Or I can use square itself as an element in some combination.
3的平方加上4的平方的和是多少
I can say, what's the sum of the square of 3 and the square of 4?
9加上16得25
9 and 16 is 25.
我可以将square作为元素用于更复杂的式子
Or I can use square as an element in some much more complicated thing.
比如 1001的平方点的平方的平方是多少
I can say, what's the square of, the sqare of, the square of 1,001?
这就是1001点的平方的平方的平方
And there's the square of the square of the square of 1,001.
我也可以问Lisp square本身是什么
Or I can say to Lisp, what is square itself?
它的值是是什么
What's the value of that?
Lisp用一种约定的方法告诉我这是一个过程
And Lisp returns some conventional way of telling me that that's a procedure.
它返回 复合过程square
It says, "compound procedure square."
记住 square的值是一个过程
Remember, the value of square is this procedure,
而那些用星号和括号的记法
and the thing with the stars and the brackets
只是Lisp用来描述这个过程的约定
are just Lisp's conventional way of describing that.
让我们再看两个关于define的例子
Let's look at two more examples of defining.
这有两个过程
Here are two more procedures.
定义x和y的平均值为x加上y的和除以2的商
I can define the average of x and y to be the sum of x and y divided by 2.
以及定义好平方和平均值后 我可以定义均方
Or having had average and mean square, having had average and square,
我可以用它们来讨论某元素的均方
I can use that to talk about the mean square of something,
即x的平方与y的平方的平均值
which is the average of the square of x and the square of y.
当定义好它们后 我可以问
So for example, having done that, I could say,
2和3的均方是多少
what's the mean square of 2 and 3?
我将会得到 4和9的平均值 即6.5
And I should get the average of 4 and 9, which is 6.5.
关键点在于 定义了square后
The key thing here is that, having defined square,
我可以把它当作一个基本元素来使用
I can use it as if it were primitive.
因此在这里
So if we look here on the slide,
我在讨论均方的时候
if I look at mean square,
从这点来说 定义均方的人没有必要知道
the person defining mean square doesn't have to know, at this point,
究竟square是由语言内建支持
whether square was something built into the language
还是自定义的过程
or whether it was a procedure that was defined.
这是Lisp的关键之一
And that's a key thing in Lisp,
你无法准确区别
that you do not make arbitrary distinctions between things
哪些是语言的基本对象 哪些是语言的内建支持
that happen to be primitive in the language and things that happen to be built in.
用户使用时则无需关心这些
A person using that shouldn't even have to know.
你自己构建的东西看起来就像是语言自带的基本对象
So the things you construct get used with all the power and flexibility
具有同样的能力和灵活性
as if they were primitives.
大家可以在课后上机做做测试
In fact, you can drive that home by looking on the computer one more time.
我们接下来讨论一下“+”吧
We talked about plus.
好的 让我们在计算机中看看
And in fact, if I come here on the computer screen and say,
“+”的值是什么
what is the value of plus?
注意Lisp在下面的输出
Notice what Lisp types out. On the bottom there, it typed out,
复合过程“+”
"compound procedure plus."
因为在此系统中
Because, in this system,
“+”运算符是一个复合过程
it turns out that the addition operator is itself a compound procedure.
但如果我不输入进去做下测试 你永远不会知道
And if I didn't just type that in, you'd never know that,
所以这没什么不同
and it wouldn't make any difference anyway.
我们并不关心这些
We don't care.
它比我们日常处理的问题更加抽象一些
It's below the level of the abstraction that we're dealing with.
其关键点在于你无法分辨出
So the key thing is you cannot tell, should not be able to tell, in general,
内建元素与复合元素之间的不同
the difference between things that are built in and things that are compound.
为什么会这样呢？
Why is that?
因为复合元素经过了一次抽象封装 (以致于无法分辨)
Because the things that are compound have an abstraction wrapper wrapped around them.
我们已经介绍了Lisp的大多数元素了
We've seen almost all the elements of Lisp now.
还有一个需要进行讨论的
There's only one more we have to look at,
就是如何进行分情况分析
and that is how to make a case analysis.
举个例子
Let me show you what I mean.
让我们考虑绝对值函数的数学定义
We might want to think about the mathematical definition of the absolute value functions.
我或许会说x的绝对值这样是一个函数
I might say the absolute value of x is the function
若x小于0 则为-x
which has the property that it's negative of x. For x less than 0,
若x等于0 则为0
it's 0 for x equal to 0.
若x大于0 则就是x
And it's x for x greater than 0.
而Lisp则有一套分情况分析方法
And Lisp has a way of making case analyses.
以绝对值定义为例 我给大家说明一下
Let me define for you absolute value.
定义绝对值为 x是有多种情况的
Say define the absolute value of x is conditional.
这就是分情况分析
This means case analysis, COND.
如果x小于0 则结果为-x
If x is less than 0, the answer is negate x.
我这里写的是一个子句
What I've written here is a clause.
这整个是一个由两部分组成的条件表达式
This whole thing is a conditional clause, and it has two parts.
这个部分叫做谓词或者条件
This part here is a predicate or a condition.
这就是一个条件
That's a condition.
用以表达条件的东西叫做谓词
And the condition is expressed by something called a predicate,
Lisp中的谓词是一种
and a predicate in Lisp is some sort of thing
可以返回true或者false的东西
that returns either true or false.
比如说“小于”是Lisp中的一个基本过程
And you see Lisp has a primitive procedure, less-than,
它返回true或者false
that tests whether something is true or false.
子句其余部分为一个动作或者需要做的事
And the other part of a clause is an action or a thing to do,
本例中为true
in the case where that's true.
在这里 我则是取x的相反数
And here, what I'm doing is negating x.
有趣的是 Lisp中减运算符符与相反数运算符是同一个
The negation operator, the minus sign in Lisp is a little bit funny.
如果有两个及两个以上的参数
If there's two or more arguments,
正如我们看到的 假设刚好有两个参数 就从第一个中减去第二个
if there's two arguments it subtracts the second one from the first, and we saw that.
如果只有一个参数 则取其相反数
And if there's one argument, it negates it.
这与前面相符合
So this corresponds to that.
这又是一个COND子句
And then there's another COND clause.
这是说 在x等于0的时候 结果为0
It says, in the case where x is equal to 0, the answer is 0.
在x大于0的时候 结果为x
And in the case where x is greater than 0, the answer is x.
闭合子句 闭合COND 闭合define
Close that clause. Close the COND. Close the definition.
这就是绝对值的定义
And there's the definition of absolute value.
你会发现分情况分析
And you see it's the case analysis that looks very much
与数学中所用的非常相似
like the case analysis you use in mathematics.
当然还有一些不常用的受限的分情况分析方法
There's a somewhat different way of writing a restricted case analysis.
很多时候 你在进行分情况分析时只有一种情况
Often, you have a case analysis where you only have one case,
你首先进行测试
where you test something,
然后根据返回的为true或false来决定如何处理
and then depending on whether it's true or false, you do something.
这是另外一种定义绝对值的方法
And here's another definition of absolute value
但看起来是几乎一样的
which looks almost the same,
像这样 如果x小于0 结果则为x的相反数
which says, if x is less than 0, the result is negate x.
否则 结果即为x
Otherwise, the answer is x.
我们将会大量的使用“if”
And we'll be using "if" a lot.
再次声明
But again, the thing to remember is that
你们在这里看到的绝对值形式
this form of absolute value that you're looking at here,
和我在黑板上写的那种
and then this one over here that I wrote on the board,
本质上是一样的
are essentially the same.
而“if”和“COND”则是
And "if" and COND are-- well, whichever way you like it.
你可以把“COND”当做“if”的语法糖
You can think of COND as syntactic sugar for "if",
或者“if”是“COND”的语法糖
or you can think of "if" as syntactic sugar for COND,
这没什么区别
and it doesn't make any difference.
Lisp系统的设计者会从中会选择一个
The person implementing a Lisp system will pick one
然后依照这个来实现另外一个
and implement the other in terms of that.
你首先实现哪一个都无所谓
And it doesn't matter which one you pick.
让我们停下来 解决几点疑问
Why don't we break now, and then take some questions.
为什么我有时用define时
How come sometimes when I write define,
我在这里使用了一个左括号
I put an open paren here and say,
输入 define (XXX
define open paren something or other,
而有时我这样写时却没加左括号
and sometimes when I write this, I don't put an open paren?
是因为你所见的
The answer is, this particular form of "define",
这种 “define” 表达式
where you say define some expression,
对于定义过程来讲是非常特殊
is this very special thing for defining procedures.
再次强调 这实际上是说我定义这个叫square的符号为这个
But again, what it really means is I'm defining this symbol, square, to be that.
你所知道的则是 你先写一个“define”
So the way you should think about it is what "define" does is you write "define",
然后你再写一个符号 没有左括号
and the second thing you write is the symbol here-- no open paren--
这是你将要定义的符号
the symbol you're defining
这又是你要将其定义为什么
and what you're defining it to be.
就像这儿和这儿
That's like here and like here.
这是“define”的基本使用方法
That's sort of the basic way you use "define."
然而 这种特殊的语法技巧
And then, there's this special syntactic trick
使得你可以定义像这样的过程
which allows you to define procedures that look like this.
因此区别就在于你是否定义了一个过程
So the difference is, it's whether or not you're defining a procedure.
[音乐]
[JESU, JOY OF MAN'S DESIRING]
信不信由你 你们已经学了足够多的Lisp的知识了
Well, believe it or not, you actually now know enough Lisp
现在你基本上可以编写
to write essentially any numerical procedure
FORTRAN、Basic或者其它语言中一样的
that you'd write in a language like FORTRAN or Basic or whatever,
数值计算过程了
or, essentially, any other language.
或许你会说 这不可能
And you're probably saying, that's not believable,
因为你知道这些语言有
because you know that these languages have things
像“for”语句和“do-until-whil”语句的东西
like "for statements", and "do until while" or something.
实际上这些我们一点也用不着
But we don't really need any of that.
本课中我们一点也不会使用这些东西
In fact, we're not going to use any of that in this course.
我给你们来个下马威
Let me show you.
回过头来看看平方根
Again, looking back at square root,
让我们看看亚历山大的Heron提出的平方根算法
let's go back to this square root algorithm of Heron of Alexandria.
想想它是怎么说的
Remember what that said.
算法说 为了找到X的平方根的近似值
It said, to find an approximation to the square root of X,
你做出猜测
you make a guess,
然后通过取guess和X/guess的平均数来改进猜测
you improve that guess by averaging the guess and X over the guess.
你不断改进猜测 直到这个猜测足够好
You keep improving that until the guess is good enough.
我已经提到过这种想法
I already alluded to the idea.
这种想法是说 如果你最初采用的猜测
The idea is that, if the initial guess that you took
真真切切的等于X的平方根
was actually equal to the square root of X,
那么G就会等于X/G
then G here would be equal to X/G.
如果你算出平方根 对其取平均数并不会改变它
So if you hit the square root, averaging them wouldn't change it.
如果你所采用的G比X的平方根大
If the G that you picked was larger than the square root of X,
那么X/G就会比X的平方根小
then X/G will be smaller than the square root of X,
因此当你取G与X/G的平均值时
so that when you average G and X/G,
就得到了两者之间的某数
you get something in between.
同理 若你采用的G过小 答案则会过大
So if you pick a G that's too small, your answer will be too large.
如果你采用了一个太大的G
If you pick a G that's too large,
如果你的G比X的平方根还要大的话
if your G is larger than the square root of X
X/G就会比X的平方根还要小
and X/G will be smaller than the square root of X.
因此取平均值使得你总可以得到两者间的某数
So averaging always gives you something in between.
#TBD
And then, it's not quite trivial, but it's possible to show that,
事实上 如果G只差X的平方根一点的话
in fact, if G misses the square root of X by a little bit,
G和X/G的平均值就会慢慢的向X的平方根靠近
the average of G and X/G will actually keep getting closer to the square root of X.
只要你不断的这样做
So if you keep doing this enough,
最终就可以不断地靠近
you'll eventually get as close as you want.
另外一个事实则是
And then there's another fact,
你总可以使用1作为一个初始猜测值来开始计算
that you can always start out this process by using 1 as an initial guess.
它总是朝X的平方根聚拢
And it'll always converge to the square root of X.
这就是亚历山大的Heron的连续求平均值法
So that's this method of successive averaging due to Heron of Alexandria.
让我们在Lisp中实现
Let's write it in Lisp.
中心思想是
Well, the central idea is,
尝试将guess作为X的平方根的一个猜想意味着什么
what does it mean to try a guess for the square root of X?
我来编码
Let's write that.
定义（try guess x）
So we'll say, define to try a guess for the square root of X,
我们该如何做 我们会说
what do we do? We'll say,
如果猜测精确到可以作为X的平方根
if the guess is good enough to be a guess for the square root of X,
那么我们就可以将这个猜测作为答案
then, as an answer, we'll take the guess.
否则 我们就会尝试改进猜测
Otherwise, we will try the improved guess.
我们将通过改进这个猜测来作为X的平方根
We'll improve that guess for the square root of X,
并尝试是否为X平方根
and we'll try that as a guess for the square root of X.
闭合try 闭合if 闭合define
Close the "try." Close the "if." Close the "define."
这就是我们如何尝试一个猜测
So that's how we try a guess.
然后 这个过程的下一步是说
And then, the next part of the process said,
为了计算平方根
in order to compute square roots, we'll say,
定义计算X的平方根为
define to compute the square root of X,
从1作为X的平方根的一个猜测开始尝试
we will try 1 as a guess for the square root of X.
我们必须定义一些其它的东西
Well, we have to define a couple more things.
我们必须说明 一个猜测如何才叫“足够好”
We have to say, how is a guess good enough?
我们又该如何改进这个猜测
And how do we improve a guess?
那么让我们来看看
So let's look at that.
而改进一个X的平方根的一个猜测的算法则是
The algorithm to improve a guess for the square root of X,
取平均数
we average-- that was the algorithm--
我们取guess和X/guess的平均数
we average the guess with the quotient of dividing X by the guess.
这就是我们如何改进一个猜测
That's how we improve a guess.
为了确定一个猜测是否足够精确 我们需要做一下规定
And to tell whether a guess is good enough, well, we have to decide something.
假设这个是X的平方根的一个猜测
This is supposed to be a guess for the square root of X,
你可能做的一件事就是
so one possible thing you can do is say,
当你采用这个猜测并将其平方
when you take that guess and square it,
你会得到一个非常接近于X的数
do you get something very close to X?
而表达这个想法的一种方式是
So one way to say that is to say,
我们用X减去guess的平方
I square the guess, subtract X from that,
并且确认所得结果的绝对值是否
and see if the absolute value of that
比一个由你规定的很小的数还要小
whole thing is less than some small number, which depends on my purposes.
因此 我们就有了计算X的平方根的一整套过程
So there's a complete procedure for how to compute the square root of X.
我们再来深入观察一下这个结构
Let's look at the structure of that a little bit.
我搞定了整件事
I have the whole thing.
我有一个用于计算X的平方根的记号
I have the notion of how to compute a square root.
这是一种模块
That's some kind of module.
也是一种黑盒
That's some kind of black box.
它的定义依赖于如何尝试将一个猜测值作为X的平方根
It's defined in terms of how to try a guess for the square root of X.
定义try是用来
"Try" is defined in terms of, well,
确认某数是否足够精确以及如何去改进该数
telling whether something is good enough and telling how to improve something.
这是good-enogh?
So good enough.
try的定义依赖于good-enough?和improve
"Try" is defined in terms of "good enough" and "improve".
让我们来看看我填入了些什么
And let's see what else I fill in.
如果我向下拓展这棵树
Well, I'll go down this tree.
good-enough?的定义依赖于abs和square
"Good enough" was defined in terms of absolute value, and square.
而improve的定义依赖于averaging
And improve was defined in terms of something called averaging
而其它的都是一些基本运算符
and then some other primitive operator.
平方根的定义依赖于try
Square root's defined in terms of "try".
try的定义依赖于good-enough?和improve
"Try" is defined in terms of "good enough" and "improve",
甚至依赖于try本身
but also "try" itself.
因此try也按照它如何应用于自身而进行定义
So "try" is also defined in terms of how to try itself.
额 这可能会使你有点糊涂
Well, that may give you some problems.
你的高中几何老师或许告诉过你
Your high school geometry teacher probably told you
用一个东西自己去定义自己是很不对的
that it's naughty to try and define things in terms of themselves,
因为这根本行不通
because it doesn't make sense.
这（种说法）是错的
But that's false.
有时候用一个东西自己来定义自己非常有意义
Sometimes it makes perfect sense to define things in terms of themselves.
我们来看看这个例子
And this is the case. And we can look at that.
假设我问Lisp：2的平方根是多少
We could write down what this means, and say,
我们可以写出它究竟是什么意思
suppose I asked Lisp what the square root of 2 is.
2的平方根是什么意思
What's the square root of 2 mean?
意思就是我将用1作为2的平方根的一个猜测
Well, that means I try 1 as a guess for the square root of 2.
然后我考虑 对于2的平方根来说 1是一个足够好的猜测么
Now I look. I say, gee, is 1 a good enough guess for the square root of 2?
这取决于good-enough?是如何判断的
And that depends on the test that "good enough" does.
本例中 good-enough?会说
And in this case, "good enough" will say,
不 对于2的平方根来说 1不是一个足够好的猜测
no, 1 is not a good enough guess for the square root of 2.
因此我会继续说 我试试一个改进值
So that will reduce to saying, I have to try an improved--
改进猜测值1
improve 1 as a guess for the square root of 2,
然后将其作为2的平方根的一个猜测
and try that as a guess for the square root of 2.
改进猜测值1用作2的平方根
Improving 1 as a guess for the square root of 2
也就是说我取1和2/1的平均值
means I average 1 and 2 divided by 1.
因此我们将取平均数
So this is going to be average.
这段代码将会取1和2/1的平均数
This piece here will be the average of 1 and the quotient of 2 by 1.
那么这段代码
That's this piece here.
我算算 结果是1.5
And I'm gonna try... And this is 1.5.
因此这个(sqrt 2)还原到(try 1 2)
So this square root of 2 reduces to trying 1 for the square root of 2,
然后还原到(try 1.5 2)
which reduces to trying 1.5 as a guess for the square root of 2.
因此这行得通
So that makes sense.
让我们看下剩下的步骤
Let's look at the rest of the process.
如果我尝试1.5 则会还原到
If I try 1.5, that reduces.
1.5作为2的平方根的猜测 并不是足够好
1.5 turns out to be not good enough as a guess for the square root of 2.
然后又还原到
So that reduces to trying the average of
(try (average 1.5 (/ 2 1.5)))
1.5 and 2 divided by 1.5 as a guess for the square root of 2.
平均值是1.333
That average turns out to be 1.333.
然后整个事又还原到(try 1.3333 2)
So this whole thing reduces to trying 1.333 as a guess for the square root of 2.
如此进行下去
And then so on.
然后又还原到(good-enough? 1.4)或者其它的
That reduces to another called a "good enough", 1.4 something or other.
然后这个（步骤）会持续进行到
And then it keeps going until the process finally stops
good-enough?认为足够好了才停止
with something that "good enough" thinks is good enough, which,
本例中 是1.4242或者其它的东西
in this case, is 1.4142 something or other.
因此这个这个过程运行得非常完美
So the process makes perfect sense.
这种定义方法叫做“递归定义”
This, by the way, is called a recursive definition.
进行递归定义将会给你带来无穷威力
And the ability to make recursive definitions is a source of incredible power.
之前我已提到过
And as you can already see I've hinted at,
递归定义可以在不增加任何负担的前提下
it's the thing that effectively allows you to do these infinite computations
仅仅通过调用过程 在达到条件之前
that go on until something is true,
完成无限次的计算
without having any other constricts other than the ability to call a procedure.
还有一点要说明的
Well, let's see, there's one more thing.
我再在这里给你们演示另外一种平方根的定义方法
Let me show you a variant of this definition of square root here on the slide.
这两种方法看起来像是一样的
Here's sort of the same thing.
在这儿 我把improve、good-enough?、try的定义
What I've done here is packaged the definitions of
全都封装在了sqrt里面
"improve" and "good enough" and "try" inside "square root".
因此实际上 我们构建了一个平方根盒子
So, in effect, what I've done is I've built a square root box.
我构建了一个其它人可以使用的平方根盒子
So I've built a box that's the square root procedure that someone can use.
它们输入36 然后（盒子）输出6
They might put in 36 and get out 6.
但是 盒子里面封装的过程
And then, packaged inside this box
就是try、good-enough?和improve的定义
are the definitions of "try" and "good enough" and "improve."
它们都隐藏在盒子里面
So they're hidden inside this box.
这样做是因为
And the reason for doing that is that,
如果有人正在使用这个平方根
if someone's using this square root,
如果George正在使用这个平方根
if George is using this square root,
George并不会关心
George probably doesn't care very much that,
当我在实现平方根时
when I implemented square root,
我定义了盒子内的那些try、good-enough?和improve过程
I had things inside there called "try" and "good enough" and "improve".
事实上 Harry可能会实现一个也具有
And in fact, Harry might have a cube root procedure
try、good-enough?和improve的立方根盒子
that has "try" and "good enough" and "improve".
因此 为了不让整个系统变得混乱
And in order to not get the whole system confused,
Harry最好把这些内部过程封装在它的立方根过程里
it'd be good for Harry to package his internal procedures inside his cube root procedure.
这个叫做块结构
Well, this is called block structure,
这是把东西打包到定义内部的一种方法
this particular way of packaging internals inside of a definition.
让我们回过头来再看看
And let's go back and look at the slide again.
读取这种过程的方法就是来定义平方根 #TBD 需要确认上下文
The way to read this kind of procedure is to say, to define "square root",
那么 在其内部
well, inside that definition,
我们已有improve的定义
I'll have the definition of an "improve" and
我们已有good-enough?和try的定义
the definition of "good enough" and the definition of "try."
以及这些定义的实体
And then, subject to those definitions,
我求平方根的定义实体是从1开始尝试
the way I do square root is to try 1.
注意这里 我不必将X当做参数传递
And notice here, I don't have to say 1 as a guess for the square root of X,
因为它们都在平方根内部
because since it's all inside the square root,
它相当于已知这个X了
it sort of has this X known.
我来总结下
Let me summarize.
我们从表述指令性知识
We started out with the idea that
开始学习
what we're going to be doing is expressing imperative knowledge.
事实上 如果从Lisp这边总结的话
And in fact, here's a slide that summarizes the way we looked at Lisp.
我们从基本元素如“+”和“*”开始
We started out by looking at some primitive elements in addition and multiplication,
一些用于测试某物小于或等于的谓词
some predicates for testing whether something is less-than or something's equal.
事实上 我们正在使用的系统掩盖了很多细节
And in fact, we saw really sneakily in the system we're actually using,
这些并不是系统的基本元素 但这无所谓
these aren't actually primitives, but it doesn't matter.
重要的是我们会把它们当作是基本元素
What matters is we're going to use them as if they're primitives.
我们不会去研究系统的内部
We're not going to look inside.
我们也有一些基本数据和一些数
We also have some primitive data and some numbers.
我们学习了合成的手段 组合的手段
We saw some means of composition, means of combination,
用运算符和操作数合成函数和构建组合式
the basic one being composing functions and
的基本方法
building combinations with operators and operands.
还有一些像是“COND”、“if”和“define”的东西
And there were some other things, like COND and "if" and "define".
具体来说 关于“define”的重点则是
But the main thing about "define," in particular,
它是一种进行抽象的方法
was that it was the means of abstraction.
它是我们为某物命名的方法
It was the way that we name things.
我们之前提到过  从这里也可以看出来
You can also see from this slide not only where we've been,
有时候 我们需要研究如何通过组合基本数据来得到复合数据
At some point, we'll have to talk about how you combine primitive data to get compound data,
以及如何抽象数据 使得你可以在一个更大的环境中
and how you abstract data so you can use large globs of data
将其当作基本数据使用
as if they were primitive.
这也是我们的目的所在
So that's where we're going.
在我们讨论这个问题之前 下节课我们首先将会讨论
But before we do that, for the next couple of lectures we're going to be talking about,
我们编写的过程与机器内部
first of all, how it is that you make a link
进程之间的联系
between these procedures we write and the processes that happen in the machine.
接着 我们将跳出小规模的计算问题
And then, how it is that you start using the power of Lisp
来学习如何发挥Lisp的威力
to talk not only about these individual little computations,
来解决更加通用的计算问题
but about general conventional methods of doing things.
好了 大家还有什么问题么
OK, are there any questions?
学生：在定义A时 如果我们用一个括号将A括起来
AUDIENCE: Yes. If we defined A using parentheses instead of as we did,
会与不使用括号不同么？
what would be the difference?
教授：如果我这样写
PROFESSOR: If I wrote this, if I wrote that,
我则会是定义一个过程并命名为A
what I would be doing is defining a procedure named A.
本例中 这个过程没有参数
In this case, a procedure of no arguments, which,
而当我运行它 则会返回5乘以5
when I ran it, would give me back 5 times 5.
学生：我的意思是
AUDIENCE: Right. I mean, you come up with the same thing,
#TBD 我没有看视频，也无法确切知道上下文
except for you really got a different--
教授：好 的确会有不同 之前的那一个
PROFESSOR: Right. And the difference would be, in the old one--
我还是在这里写清楚一点吧
Let me be a little bit clearer here.
我们还是把这个叫做A
Let's call this A, like here.
作为对比 我们假装这里有一个
And pretend here, just for contrast, I wrote,
我定义D为5乘以5
define D to be the product of 5 and 5.
这两者的区别则是
And the difference between those,
让我们看看它们在Lisp解释器中是怎样的
let's think about interactions with the Lisp interpreter.
我在Lisp中键入A 返回25
I could type in A and Lisp would return 25.
如果我仅仅键入D
I could type in D, if I just typed in D,
Lisp返回复合过程D
Lisp would return compound procedure D,
因为D就是一个过程
because that's what it is. It's a procedure.
我可以运行D 我可以问运行D的结果是什么
I could run D. I could say, what's the value of running D?
这是一个没有运算数的组合式
Here is a combination with no operands.
我考虑到它没有运算数 所以我在D后面没有键入任何东西
I see there are no operands. I didn't put any after D.
Lisp则会说结果是25
And it would say, oh, that's 25.
我再说周全一点 如果我键入 A的运行结果是多少
Or I could say, just for completeness, if I typed in, what's the value of running A?
只能得到一个错误
I get an error.
跟这里的错误一样
The error would be the same one as over there.
这个错误是因为 A的值——25
It'd be the error would say, sorry, 25, which is the value of A,
并不是我可以应用于某物的运算符
is not an operator that I can apply to something.
MIT OpenCourseWare
http://ocw.mit.edu
本项目主页
https://github.com/FoOTOo/Learning-SICP